Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Department Records 1765, 1830-2018 NYHS-RG 20
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Curatorial and Administration Files, 1934-2013; 167875; 39.92 Linear feet
  - Subseries III.D. Holly Hotchner Files, 1970-1994; 169760; 14.83 Linear feet
    Internal note: There are few, if any, files in the subseries concerning conservation treatment of specific objects as these files were returned to the museum during processing in 2016. Personnel evaluation files were removed and turned over to Human Resources in 2016. Documents concerning routine administrative transactions, such as invoices for supplies and travel expense requests, were discarded. Most general reference materials, such as photocopies of technical conservation guidance and vendor marketing material, were discarded.
    The subseries includes, at least primarily, the files of Holly Hotchner. (Some files of other museum personnel, including former curator Ella Foshay (1984-1989), were likely mixed in with these when stored.) These represent the range of Hotchner's activities from her early years in conservation to her later years as Museum Director. The files range from general conservation matters, storage and warehousing, object surveys and inventories, some exhibition and special event planning, and professional activities. Particular initiatives that are well-represented in the subseries include the licensing arrangements with Birchrun Mint to reproduce one of the Rogers groups, "Weighing the Baby", conservation of the Louis XVI chair, planning for new storage at Crozier Warehouse in 1990, and arrangements for the Thomas Cole: Landscape into History and Equitable Gallery exhibitions. There are many files related to outgoing loans, though these may simply be additional files that were inadvertently separated from the bulk of loan files found in Series IV. Collection Management Files. Fuller summaries of the content are provided in the container list below. Certain files related to Hotchner's activities as Museum Director during the 1990s are currently restricted. See the Access Restrictions note.
    - Conservation. General (32 folders), 1970, 1983-1994; 169778 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 1-32)
      Internal note: About 20 folders concerning restoration of specific museum and Print Room objects were returned to Alan Balicki and Marybeth Kavanagh, respectively.
      Includes general conservation matters, including budgets (1984-90), conservation studio opening announcements, summary of interns, job position advertisements, environmental/climate control/lighting, and some general damage assessments.
    - Paintings, Frames, Drawings, Miniatures (7 of 32 folders), 1981-1994; 169779 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 33-39)
      Includes files concerning condition surveys, priorities, appraisals, inquiries, and other such matters. Specific collections noted include: Abrams Portfolio, T.J. Bryan, City of Plainfield Bierstadt paintings, Thomas William Channing Moore, Mary Stuart, Nora Durand Woodman, landscape and genre paintings (R.G. Wunderlich appraisal of 1984), miniatures, and Luman Reed frames.
    - Paintings, Frames, Drawings, Miniatures (21 of 32 folders), 1981-1994; 170279 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 1-21)
    - Paintings, Frames, Drawings, Miniatures (4 of 32 folders), 1981-1994; 170280 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 1-4)
    - Sculpture. General (3 folders), 1990-1992; 169780 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 5-7)
      Principally concerns a conservation survey and assessment.
    - Sculpture. Birchrun Mint License (4 folders), 1989-1992; 169781 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 8-11)
      Concerns reproduction rights for "Weighing the Baby" from the Rogers Group.
    - Prints, Photographs, & Architectural (11 folders), 1979-1993; 169782 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 1-11)
      Includes files on conservation, surveys, general descriptions, inquiries, consideration of transferring the Print Room collections from the museum to the library, and other such matters. Specific collections referred to include: James H. Hyde, Ferdinand Ogden, Cass Gilbert, McComb, Landauer, and McKim Mead & White.
    - Decorative Arts (16 of 35 folders), 1975-1993; 169783 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 12-27)
      Includes files concerning surveys, descriptions, appraisals, and conservation of furniture, carriages, silver, and Tiffany glass. Several of the files concern the Louis XVI side chair (1817.13). Other specific objects include the Duncan Phyfe tool chest, the Connecticut House facade (from Prentis-Murphy), the Steinway Hose carriage, and DePeyster, Beekman, Nadelman, and LeBoeuf collections. An oversize plan was removed from a folder into an oversize box noted below.
    - Decorative Arts (19 of 35 folders), 1975-1993; 170284 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 1-19)
    - Decorative Arts. Oversize, 1985; 169812 (Box 274, Folder 11)
      Includes an oversize plan of the Phyfe tool chest by Carlyle Lynch.
    - Storage & Warehousing (9 of 44 folders), 1983-1993; 169811 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 20-28)
      Includes files concerning the planning for the transfer of objects (principally paintings and decorative art) stored at Central Park West and off-site to a new offsite location (Crozier Fine Arts, Inc. on West 20th Street) in 1990. Includes storage and floor plan blueline drawings by architects Allan Greenberg and Richard Jansen. Oversize plans were removed from folders into an oversize drawer noted below.
    - Storage & Warehousing (30 of 44 folders), 1983-1993; 170286 (Offsite-box 111, Folder 1-30)
    - Storage & Warehousing (5 of 44 folders), 1983-1993; 170288 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 1-5)
    - Storage & Warehousing. Oversize, 1989-1990; 169813 (Drawer 12A-B9, Folder 18)
      Includes oversize storage and shelving plans removed from the above files.
    - Museum Design/Facilities (8 folders), 1989-1991; 169814 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 6-12)
      Includes files related to redesigning some of N-YHS's exhibition space, including files on architects Allan Greenberg and Richard Jansen, and lighting consultant George Sexton. See also New-York Historical Society (NYHS-RG 4) for much more on N-YHS's planned renovations during this period.
    - Museum Design/Facilities. Oversize, 1990; 169815 (Drawer 12A-B9, Folder 18)
      Includes an oversize plan by Richard Jansen of the 3rd floor corridor lay-out (i.e., West Hall offices).
    - General Museum Administration (9 of 35 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1987-1993; 169816 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 13-21)
      Includes files concerning the administration of the museum department, including general collection descriptions, museum policies and procedures (e.g., loan procedures), job descriptions and staffing, museum/library connections, and general employee policies.
    - General Museum Administration (26 of 35 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1987-1993; 170290 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 1-26)
    - Planning & Reports (25 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1993; 169817 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 1-25)
      Includes the Museum Department's annual and other periodic progress reports and long-range planning documents. Also includes a file of memos between Hotchner and curator Annette Blaugrund concerning exhibition planning, public relations, and various other museum managerial matters.
    - Fiscal Crisis Correspondence & Articles (17 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1988-1994; 170188 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 1-17)
      Includes original correspondence to Hotchner, or forwarded to her by others at N-YHS, and photocopies of Hotchner's response. This correspondence concerns various matters related to N-YHS's publicized financial difficulties including expressions of interest in acquiring any dispositions and expressions of general concern about N-YHS's condition. Routine matters are also represented including offers of donations of objects, requests for loans, and research visit requests. The folders also include clippings, general staff memos, and other generally distributed matter.
    - Budgets and Financial Information (14 of 26 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1988-1994; 170197 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 1-14)
      Includes working files, memos, budgets, alternate planning assumptions, projections, actual expenses, and some financial statements. Principally concerns Museum Department budgets and expenses, but other departments of N-YHS also appear.
    - Budgets and Financial Information (12 of 26 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1989-1994; 170294 (Offsite-box 117, Folder 1-12)
    - Grants & Development (24 of 101 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1994; 170219 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 1-24)
      Includes general files concerning grant and fundraising possibilities, priorities, summaries, deadlines, and reports. Generally these concern funding for conservation initiatives and exhibitions. Files on specific sources of grants in this box include the Annenberg Foundation, Charles Dana Foundation, Department of Cultural Affairs, Dunlevy Milbank Foundation, and Florence Gould Foundation.
    - Grants & Development (20 of 101 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1994; 170402 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 1-20)
      This box includes files on grants from the Getty (Louis XVI chair), Institute of Museum Services (IMS) (sculptures), Kunstadter Family Foundation, Henry Luce Foundation (primarily the McKim Mead & White and Thomas Hotchkiss exhibitions), and National Endowment of the Arts (NEA) and National Endowment of the Humanities (NEH).
    - Grants & Development (24 of 101 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1994; 170403 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 1-24)
      This box includes files on proposed grants and approved grants from the National Endowment of the Arts (NEA) and National Endowment of the Humanities (NEH). These include Cass Gilbert conservation and Thomas Hotchkiss paintings conservation and exhibition (includes color slides), among others. Also includes files on New York City and state grants.
    - Grants & Development (10 of 101 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1994; 170421 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 1-10)
      This box includes files on proposed grants from the National Endowment of the Arts (NEA) and National Endowment of the Humanities (NEH) for the Tenth Street Studio exhibition. Also includes NEH for a negatives conservation grant (denied), Starr Foundation, and Warhol Foundation (Cass Gilbert exhibition and catalogue).
    - Grants & Development (23 of 101 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030, 1985-1994; 170464 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 1-23)
      This box includes some general grant files, but most relate to initiatives cultivating financial support including membership, corporate sponsorships, creation of the Architects Circle steering/advisory committee for N-YHS's architecture collections, and creation of the Friends of Conservation group.
    - Acquisitions (36 of 47 folders), 1985-1994; 170465 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 1-36)
      Includes folders concerning general policies and information about accessions and deaccessions, proposed gifts, bequests and other acquisitions (including rejected objects), and photoccopies of correspondence and other documents related to specific acquisitions of paintings, drawings, sculpture, decorative arts, prints, and photographs.
    - Acquisitions (11 of 47 folders), 1985-1994; 170487 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 1-11)
    - Exhibitions. General (8 of 9 folders), 1985-1994; 170511 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 12-19)
      Includes files of exhibition proposals (including a proposed touring exhibition of the Neustadt Tiffany collection in 1985), rejected proposals, schedules, and the like.
    - Exhibitions. General (1 of 9 folders), 1993-1994; 170512 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 1)
    - Exhibitions. U.S. Constitution: Government by Choice, 1986; 170513 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 2)
    - Exhibitions. Cased Images and Irving Browning, 1989; 170514 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 3)
    - Exhibitions. Tiffany, 1988-1990; 170515 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 4)
    - Exhibitions. Audubon (6 folders), 1980-1992; 170516 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 5-10)
      Includes materials related to various Audubon exhibitions and proposed exhibitions.
    - Exhibitions. Tenth Street Studio; Portrait Gallery, 1992; 170517 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 11)
      Includes an overall description of the proposed Tenth Street exhibition and label text for the Portrait Gallery.
    - Exhibitions. Collection Re-Installation, 1992-1993; 170518 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 12)
    - Exhibitions at Sony Corp., 1993; 170519 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 13)
    - Exhibitions. Creating American Cultural Heroes, 1994; 170520 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 14)
    - Exhibitions. 2 X Immortal: Elvis & Marilyn, 1994; 170521 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 15)
    - Exhibitions. Thomas Cole: Landscape into History (16 folders), 1992-1994; 170522 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 1-16)
      Includes correspondence and agreements with the National Museum of American Art, funding proposals, press and other publicity materials, wall text, and other documents.
    - Exhibitions at The Equitable Gallery (9 folders), 1994; 170523 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 1-9)
      Includes correspondence, draft agreements, press and other publicity materials, brochure text, and other documents related to the exhibition of N-YHS objects at The Equitable.
    - Loans (12 of 51 folders), 1985-1994; 170524 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 10-21)
      Includes some general files on policies and procedures related to N-YHS's outgoing loans of objects, and files on loans denied or withdrawn during N-YHS's fiscal crisis. The following box has files related to specific loans, some for extended periods and others for specific timebound exhibitions. These files were likely inadvertently separated from other loan files that were integrated into Series IV. Collection Management Files, Subseries B. Outgoing Loans.
    - Loans (39 of 51 folders), 1985-1994; 170525 (Offsite-box 128, Folder 1-39)
      Among others, the files include loans to Brooklyn Museum, Waterloo Village, War Memorial Museum of Virginia, Museums at Stony Brook, Owen Thomas Museum, New York Law Institute, Chesterwood, Department of the Navy (includes photographs of USS Monitor (1862.9) and Tingey uniform (1932.221), Monticello, Gracie Mansion, Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, Baltimore Museum of Art, Colonial Williamsburg, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Tokyo Metropolitan Government, Bibliotheque Nationale de France, Hudson River Museum, Jordan-Volpe Gallery, National Academy of Design, Minneapolis Institute of Arts, Audubon House, National Portrait Gallery, and Brandywine River Museum.
    - Public Programs & Collections Access (23 folders), 1986-1992; 170526 (Offsite-box 129, Folder 1-23)
      Includes files concerning various public programs, including a slide show talk providing an overview of the collections (1986), publicity material for programs, summary lists, proposed visitor surveys, a study of visitor and member groups (1988), and a review of the use of museum collections and staff in education and research programs.
    - Special Events (13 folders), 1993-1994; 170527 (Offsite-box 130, Folder 1-13)
      Includes files concerning private uses of N-YHS's facilities, including for filming such as Robert Redford's Quiz Show and TV's Law and Order, and for meetings of Community Advisory Board 7, the Alliance for the Arts, and Bard College's Decorative Arts program symposium. The files also reference film rights for material, including for Florentine Films' series The Civil War.
    - Professional Activities and Miscellaneous (9 of 37 folders), 1984-1994; 170528 (Offsite-box 130, Folder 14-22)
      These files include documents related to N-YHS's and Hotchner's professional affiliations, such as with the Association of American Museums and sponsoring student studies at N-YHS, and Hotchner's professional activities outside of N-YHS, particularly in terms of lectures on conservation. There are also a small number of files on subjects that did not fit clearly into other categories.
    - Professional Activities and Miscellaneous (28 of 37 folders), 1978-1994; 170529 (Offsite-box 131, Folder 1-37)
  - Subseries III.E. Annette Blaugrund Files, 1989-1995; 170530; 2.63 Linear feet
    The subseries includes, at least in large part, the files of Annette Blaugrund, Senior Curator of Paintings, Drawing & Sculpture from 1989-1995. The files include correspondence concerning proposed exhibitions, research inquiries, offers of objects for accession, and other museum matters. The files also include object surveys, especially for sculpture, and general administration and exhibition planning documents. Fuller summaries of the content are provided in the container list below. Certain of Blaugrund's files are currently restricted. See the Access Restrictions note. A major initiative of Blaugrund's was the planning for an exhibition about the Tenth Street Studio Building. This subseries holds few or no files on the matter; the bulk of these were integrated at some point with other exhibition files. See Series II. Exhibitions, Subseries I. General Files, folders for Painting and Patronage: The Tenth Street Studios (1993).
    - General Correspondence & Memos (7 of 17 folders), 1991-1995; 170531 (Offsite-box 132, Folder 1-7)
      Includes correspondence and memos concerning incoming research inquiries about objects and artists, exhibition proposals, offers of objects, and other museum matters.
    - General Correspondence & Memos (10 of 17 folders), 1989-1995; 170532 (Offsite-box 133, Folder 1-10)
    - Administrative Files (4 folders), 1989-1994; 170533 (Offsite-box 133, Folder 11-14)
      Includes files concerning visitor counts, intern tasks, filing system, a museum brochure reference material, and facilities information, especially lighting recommendations for the second floor corridor gallery.
    - Collections Policies (4 folders), 1990-1994; 170534 (Offsite-box 134, Folder 1-4)
    - Exhibitions (7 of 11 folders), 1991-1995; 170535 (Offsite-box 134, Folder 5-11)
      Includes files on proposed exhibitions and planning meeting and procedures. One file includes notes concerning the Treasury of the Past (1995) exhibition and another concerns a long-term loan to the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation.
    - Exhibitions (4 of 11 folders), 1987-1995; 170536 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 1-4)
      Includes files on the Paris 1889: American Artists at the Universal Exposition and Rare Birds of China exhibitions, and a proposed Urban Gallery.
    - Research Sources (4 folders), circa 1991-1993; 170537 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 5-8)
      Includes notes and other documents identifying art research sources.
    - Object Descriptions & Inventories (11 of 13 folders), 1990-1994; 170538 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 9-19)
      Principally includes surveys and inventories of paintings and sculpture.
    - Object Descriptions & Inventories (2 of 13 folders), 1993; 170539 (Offsite-box 136, Folder 1-2)
      Includes a system-generated Sculpture Checklist as of April 15, 1993, by Ann Weissman.
    - Long Range Planning & Deaccessions (29 folders) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2030), 1989-1994; 170540 (Offsite-box 137, Folder 1-29)
      Includes files on meetings in connection with potential deaccessions, long-range planning task force, advisory groups, and object appraisals.
  - Subseries III.F. Margaret (Margi) Hofer Files RESTRICTED, 1992-2012; 170541; 1.67 Linear feet
    The files are in their original order. There are four sets of files, each arranged in a different manner (chronological, alphabetical, topically, by object), but the overall content is the same across the files.
    The subseries includes certain correspondence files of Margaret (Margi) Hofer. Hofer was hired in the 1990s as a consulting curator, eventually becoming Curator of Paintings, Drawings, and Sculpture. The files include patron inquiries about objects, offers of objects for sale or donation, and other generally object-oriented matters.
    As of 2016, Margi Hofer is still an active employee and consequently her files are restricted. Access may be granted with the permission of Ms. Hofer
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical. A-P (4 of 6 folders), 1992-2003; 170542 (Offsite-box 138, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical. Q-Z (2 of 6 folders), 1992-2003; 170543 (Offsite-box 139, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence, General (5 of 7 folders), 2003-2012; 170544 (Offsite-box 139, Folder 3-7)
    - Correspondence, General (2 of 7 folders), 1996-1997, 2006; 170545 (Offsite-box 140, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence, Objects (13 folders), 1996-2008; 170546 (Offsite-box 140, Folder 3-14)
    - Correspondence, Chronological (2 of 10 folders), 1992-2000; 170547 (Offsite-box 140, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence, Chronological (8 of 10 folders), 2000-2010; 170548 (Offsite-box 141, Folder 1-8)
- Series IV. Collection Management Files, 1929-2005; 167871; 25.38 Linear feet
  The Collection Management series is organized in the following subseries:
  Subseries IV.A. General Files
  Subseries IV.B. Outgoing Loans
  Subseries IV.C. Albina De Meio and Related Files
  Subseries IV.D. Luce Center Logistics
  The Collections Management series includes certain records of the Registrar and other records related to the administration of museum objects. The bulk of the series by far includes records of outgoing loans from N-YHS for exhibition or other display at other institutions; these loan records extend back to 1929. Though extensive, the loan records do not appear to include all outgoing loans.
  The series includes some records of incoming loans for some of N-YHS's exhibitions of the 1940s and 1950s. (The bulk of incoming exhibition loan records are found in Series II, Exhibitions.) This series also holds accession lists and receipts for the 1950s-1960s.
  The series also holds a few files from the 1980s-1990s covering the transport and warehousing of the collection at that time, as well as location mapping for the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, which opened in 2000.
  - Subseries IV.A. General Files, 1929-1965; 170579; 1.83 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged by subject matter and follows original order as found during processing in 2016.
    The subseries includes files from the Museum Registrar, principally Carolyn Scoon (1942-1957),Theresa Czajkowska (1950-1957), and Dorothy Hull (1958-1961). The files includes receipts for outgoing loans by N-YHS, including early (1929-1938) records of such loans. Incoming loan files, as well as the explicitly labeled files for exhibitions, document objects borrowed for exhibition at N-YHS in the 1940s-1950s. The series includes registrar receipts for other objects, such as those submitted for consideration for donation. Accessions and auction sales are documented in the working files for the annual reports and elsewhere in the subseries.
    - Notes for Annual Reports, 1949-1962; 170581 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1962; 170582 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 2)
    - Draft Manual for Museum Registrars, 1954; 170583 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 3)
    - Imaging Service Fees, 1953; 170584 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 4)
    - Thompson Homestead Museum, East Hampton, L.I., 1942-1945; 170585 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 5)
    - Material Sold, 1943-1948; 170586 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 6)
      Includes books and museum objects sent to auction.
    - Registrar Receipts (4 folders), 1956, 1960-1962; 170587 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 7-10)
    - "Hall of Great Events", circa 1937; 170588 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 11)
    - Evacuation List, 1941-1942; 170589 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Museum Accessions, etc., circa 1939-1950; 170590 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 13)
    - Receipt Books #1 and #3 for Articles Given Out or Loaned by N-YHS, 1929-1933, 1936-1938; 170593 (Offsite-box 143, Folder 1)